How would you describe the right
understanding? It seems that most people
see understanding or wisdom either as
sudden meditative experiences that
purify you from defilements miraculously
or as detailed knowledge and analytical
prowess regarding Buddhist doctrine and
the like. What is the understanding one
should seek if it's neither of these?
The understanding that used to make
people sought upon us during their
conversations with the Buddha.
Uh so yes, correct. It's neither of
those really like um people approach
Buddhism through their obviously people
get interested in some sort of spiritual
practice and then meditation and
meditation experiences and so on and
then even if they come across the sutras
even if they think they're reading the
sutas objectively they're really still
reading them through those spiritual
expectations they would have developed
and acquired beforehand such as magical
meditation experience um hypnotic
practice practices that will result in
some great revelations and so on. So
even when they read the sutras they kind
of see those things in the sutras
although if you just look at the sutras
objectively there is nothing like that
in them. I mean the best example of that
is the contemporary terravada and the
entire commentary sort of tradition
which is like reading the meditation
techniques and ideas about the practice
back into the scriptures and using it to
support itself in return. But uh if you
just put aside or if you were to not
know the commentaries and the modern u
um meditation methods, you would never
arrive at those same conclusions if you
just read the sutas the way they speak.
So so that's a problem like that bias.
It's not it can be subtle obviously that
the um the point of view you're coming
from can certainly influence how you
understand the texts, how you read them,
what you see in them. So that's why like
if you really want to know what type of
understanding the Buddha um well the
sutras talk about uh just understand the
word understanding like put aside your
understanding like put aside your
spiritual practice put aside the weight
of the tradition and but everybody else
does this and says it's right just the
sutas talk about understanding full
understanding all the time so what is
full understanding in colloquial terms
like what is
that what is it that you understand? So
you see like okay so then it's not a
magical hypnotic experience of the
revelation of the true world or
something because that's obviously not
understanding that's just
novelty. Um, on the other hand, well,
it's certainly not drawing the vast
amount of connections in space and time
through information and everything you
learned about
it. So, what is it then? Like what is
understanding? When you say understood
something, what do you mean? So
obviously you need some information, you
need some instruction in order to um
well in order to know what you need to
understand. But then is understanding in
colloquial terms measured by as I said
just a experience sort of like you're
randomly doing these practices and
waiting for something new to
happen preferably pleasant and so that
you can call it understanding or is
understanding really when you are clear
in the beginning in the middle and the
end of what you're doing and what it
leads to. So if you were to in colloquial
to. So if you were to in colloquial
terms understand any
problem you would see oh yeah there is
obviously the information I gather about
the problem but then there is the active
problem but then there is the active
effort I put to really see for
myself not just parrot what I learned
not just introduce more information more
references uh about what I learned but
it's like no I got enough but I really
need to see for myself the principle
behind behind of whatever I'm trying to
understand. And if you keep doing
that, making such effort to discern the
meaning behind, then the time will come when you
behind, then the time will come when you
will actually have the aha
moment. But at no point would you then
think that aha moment came out of your
nostril calming meditation hypnotic
technique because it didn't. It would
have come because you've been trying to
understand all these
years never letting
go of the theme of the topic of what's
important. Sure, sometimes added more
information when that was needed, but
the point is no amount of information
would have been taken at face value and
you would have been using it just to get
closer to the meaning of the principle
that you're trying to understand. And
when you understood it, as the suta
says, he knows that he knows
not like oh now I know because something
happened to me therefore that must be
sapati that's like this generic
commentarial as I said modern terraada
view uh and it's completely upside down
so even understanding in colloquial
terms it's not really obscure term it's
not really hard to understand what
understanding means but it got so
convoluted and distorted when it was
applied when it was taken and sort of
sucked into these contemporary practices
where by understanding today just means
anything from like a mystical experience
of the knowing is now or things like
that which makes no sense uh to to like
or like just just a dry study and
drawing connections and having
everything fit in your head all the
information every answer for every angle
yet the sutas go on and on about a very
simple thing suffering and the end of
it have you understood not because you
realize on information, not because you
rely on a novelty experience of your
hypnotic technique. Put both of those aside. Do
technique. Put both of those aside. Do
you know for yourself fully? Can you
explain it to others what is the
presently arisen cause of presently
arisen suffering? Can you explain to
others what is the presently arisen
escape from the presently arisen
suffering without referencing the Buddha
without referencing the sutras without
paring the phrases and stock phrases and
so on without saying well I just know
because it just happened on one retreat
no do you understand and as a result of
that understanding are you untouchable
by that
suffering so that's what understanding
is and that's why that understanding
needs to be like it's simply not
optional to develop it any other way
except on the basis of withdrawal from
everything unh wholesome on account of
virtue and sense restraint that is
creating the basis where this meaning
where this principle that the Buddha
talked about lives so to
speak so that's why you you can't as I
said you can't just stumble upon it
through trying to figure out connections of you
trying to figure out connections of you
know between the sutas and this and that
and all the different aspects that you
read and then just have like a you might
have many of aha moments when you
discover parallels oh look this suta is
saying this and that that's the same and
I had that and I remember that all of
those are forms of insight nobody's
denying that but see it's not insight
that frees you from suffering so if it's
not that insight that frees you from
suffering you shouldn't stop
there and if you already know everything
in terms of the sutas. If you have every
information yet you're still not the
sapana. Well, it's not because you're
lacking the uh instruction of another.
It's because you're lacking the other
counterpart yonisara that can only be
developed on the basis of virtue and
sense restraint like thorough
purification, withdrawal from
sensuality, celibacy like those are
prerequisite for
yonisara. I mean as the other sutas say
so many times there's not a single thing
they would make unreason desire arise
and proliferate
um and a reason sorry unreason desire
arise and a reason proliferate and
spread such as
Ioniara. So by withdrawing from
sensuality you are inadvertently even
without knowing at the time practicing
yonara developing that range so to speak
as that that factor that is a factor for
the for the right view. So when that
internal side has been sort of uh carved
out sufficiently enough through through
pressure imposed on account of the
precepts sense restraint
moderation and the instruction of
another then yes when you think about
suffering uh as I said present there is a cause
uh as I said present there is a cause
the escape the craving all the aspects
that we're going to talk about well they
do they are close to the basis where
they are where they can apply
Without it, doesn't matter the amount of
effort you put, it's just going to be
abstract. It's going to be abstracted
from that base. And it cannot possibly
result in that um well, liberation
because once the actual suffering is
understood correctly for what it is, you
can't suffer even if you want to. And
you can't go back either. It's
irreversible.